AMERICAN CHEMICAL SOCIETY:
Minnesota Historical Society
American Chemical Society records.
1913-2010.
Minnesota Historical Society
American Chemical Society. Minnesota Section.
Organizational records of the Section include minutes, reports, membership data, financial records, and correspondence, as well as historical information and official documents such as the charter, articles of incorporation, and bylaws. Also included are files concerning meetings, conferences, and symposia, particularly the series of undergraduate symposia held annually at various colleges and universities throughout Minnesota.
5.2 cubic feet (5 boxes, and 1 oversize folder in a partial box).
HISTORICAL NOTE
The Minnesota Section of the American Chemical Society was chartered in 1906 and hosted its first national meeting in 1910. In 1965, topical groups were organized to support specific interest areas such as inorganic, analytical, and polymer chemistry. Beginning in the 1950s, the section published its own journal, Minnesota Chemist.
ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION
Accession Information:
Accession number: 12,671; 12,842; 13,200; 13,222; 13,383; 13,345; 13,608; 13,788; 13,948; 14,183; 14,475; 14,710; 14,814; 15,025; 15,366; 16,326; 16,554
CATALOG HEADINGS
Topics:
Chemistry -- Minnesota -- Societies, etc.; Trade and professional associations -- Minnesota.
Organization:
American Chemical Society.
Occupation:
Chemists -- Minnesota.
RELATED MATERIALS
Along Scientific Trails: A Series of Radio Talks, published by the American Chemical Society, Minnesota Section, is separately cataloged in the Minnesota Historical Society book collection.
Minnesota Chemist, the official publication of the American Chemical Society, Minnesota Section, is separately cataloged in the Minnesota Historical Society serials collection.
DETAILED DESCRIPTION
- History and background information.
- Articles of incorporation, 1959.
- Bylaws, 1936, 1967, 1974, 1983, 1984-1988., 11 folders.
- Bylaws correspondence, 1946-1966, 1975-1979., 2 folders.
- Charter information, 1966-1968.
- Operating manuals, 1966-1969.
- Executive Committee:
  - Minutes, January 1946-June 1995., 8 folders.
  - Significant actions of the Executive Committee, 1950-1983., 2 folders.
  - Committee membership lists, 1952-1965, 1977-1989, 1992, 1995.
  - Correspondence, March 1948, June 1950-November 1954.
- Annual reports, 1948-1983., 5 folders.
  Missing: 1951, 1954, 1959.
- Annual reports, 1984-1994., 4 folders.
- Monthly membership meeting files, November 1945-April 1983., 6 folders.
  Includes notices, correspondence, programs, speech abstracts, and related papers; 1966-1983 files incomplete.
- Lists of monthly meetings, 1985-1986.
- Meeting files, 1968-1987, 2010.; 17 folders.
- Membership files:
  - Lists and related papers, 1934-1963, 1965, 1966, 1968-1970.
  - Correspondence of student affiliates, 1947-1954.
  - Minnesota-Wisconsin boundary area members: Correspondence and miscellany, 1959, 1963-1964, 1968-1969.
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous papers, 1950, 1955-1981.
    Includes membership committee correspondence.
  - Membership log, 1980.
  - Rosters, 1985-1986.
- Officers and committee chairs:
  - Lists, 1939-1978., 2 folders.
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1929, 1952-1983., 2 folders.
    Includes elections and nominating committee.
- Committee files:
  - Awards, 1934, 1952-1984., 3 folders.
  - Budget task force, 1992-1993.
  - Education, 1951-1980.
  - Polymer topical group, 1963-1977.
  - Professional status, 1945-1955, 1960-1973.
  - Publicity, 1954-1966.
    Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Speakers Bureau, 1957-1983.
  - Miscellaneous committees: Arrangements-Symposium, 1950-1984.
    Includes Minnesota Chemist Committee.
- Financial records:
  - Treasurers' reports and budgets, 1929, 1939-1947, 1950-1975.
  - Correspondence and related papers, 1950-1974.
  - Treasurer's records:
    - Norman W. Gill, 1974-1976., 5 folders.
    - Pat Fish, 1976-June 1978., 3 folders.
    - Miscellaneous records, 1978-1995.
- Symposiums, conferences, and meetings:
  - Midwest Conference of Local Sectional Activities, 1966, 1970.
  - Great Lakes Regional Meetings:
    - June 1966-June 1980.
      Incomplete.
    - St. Paul, June 1975.
    - St. Paul, June 1983.
    - 1972-1976.
  - Spring symposium, 1969.
  - Minnesota section symposiums, 1947-1970.; 2 folders.
  - Undergraduate symposiums in chemistry, 1958-1966., 3 folders.
    Symposiums held annually at various colleges and universities throughout Minnesota.
  - Undergraduate symposiums in chemistry, 1967-1994., 5 folders.
  - Miscellaneous conferences, 1990.
- General correspondence files, 1958, 1961-1988, 1992-1993., 4 folders.
- Federal legislation regarding creation of office of Technological Mobilization (1942-1943) and National Science Foundation (1945, 1947).
- First newsletter of the Minnesota Section, October 25, 1949.
- Retired chemists' pensions, 1960.
- Local section PR grant report, 1994.
- American Chemical Society (national organization):
  - Charters, constitutions, and bylaws, 1970, 1975, 1978.
  - Council minutes and related papers
    - 1961-1962, 1966.
    - 1986., 2 volumes.
  - Officers, council members, and board minutes, 1971-1980.
  - Local sections' activity reports, 1962, 1963, 1966, 1971.
  - National meetings held in Minnesota, 1929., 2 folders.
  - Seventy-fifth anniversary celebration correspondence, 1951.
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1913, 1929, 1959-1987., 2 folders.
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets and booklets, 1950-1986. 2 packets.
- Miniature tape dispenser, undated and 1955-1960.
- Minnesota Section membership roster, September 18, 1968.
  Bound computer printout listing 1,382 names.